You both do have certain predispositions
that you're getting in the same way
in which people from political correctness
are trying to say this is
what it means to be a woman.
These are the kind of things that it is
expected from a woman
to do to defend herself.
And it seems to me that you are making
a simple claim about this is what
conservative people do and this
is how they always relate to.
Well, I don't I would say that I perhaps
am doing that, but I don't see how that's
the same as what
the postmodernists are doing.
I mean, as far as I can tell,
the postmodernists aren't saying
that the groups, the individuals within
those groups are characterized by any
stable characteristics whatsoever except
for the fact of their
comparative oppression.
So I don't understand the first
part of your argument.
Part of the reason the postmodern types
have been going after me is because I
dared to say that men and women differ in
temperament, which, by the way, they do.
Now,
that's actually something that might be
worth just differentiating quickly because
it's actually
technically somewhat challenging
but also very much worth knowing.
I was debating
someone on a panel this morning on a TV
show, The Right Stuff,
and this was a woman who led the female
the Women's Equality Party,
and she cited some psychological
literature that purported to claim
that men and women were mostly the same.
And that's actually true.
We are more the same than different.
If you look at our temperaments,
there's more overlap than there is
variance by a substantial amount.
And so even on the temperamental
dimensions where there is most difference
between men and women,
the difference isn't of massive magnitude
at the center of the distribution.
So for example, women are less aggressive
than men, which is, by the way,
why they commit suicide,
try to commit suicide more often, but are
much less lethal in their actions.
That's one example.
But there are many examples.
If you draw a random woman and a random
man out of the population,
the probability that the man
will be more aggressive is 60%.
If you bet on the man,
you'd win 60% of the time.
That's not a walloping difference.
It's not 95% of the time.
It's a difference that is substantive,
it's significant, it's measurable.
But it's not large by the standards
by which such things are judged.
But that's not the point.
The point is that most of the activity
takes place at the extremes.
So out on the tails of the distribution.
So here's an example.
About nine out of ten
people in prison are male.
Why?
Because to be in prison,
you have to be the most aggressive person,
let's say in 100, okay?
Those differences at the midpoint are
large enough so that if you go out
to the extremes, one in 100 people,
you have an overwhelming
preponderance of men.
And so you can have your
cake and eat it too.
You can say, well, yeah, broadly speaking,
men and women are more
the same than different.
The overlap is greater than
the disjunction.
But that's not relevant if what's being
selected is often at the extremes,
and it often is.
So for example,
with regards to engineering,
there's a fair bit of evidence that people
who are more interested in things
than in people become engineers.
Now, that's not really going
to be what is that shocking?
Are you shocked by that?
You shouldn't be shocked by that, right?
You can you can tell that not only by what
engineers do, but you can
tell that by how they think.
And you can tell that just by talking
to them if you know a bunch of engineers.
And it turns out that the largest
temperamental difference that's known
between men and women is actually interest
in people versus interest in things.
And so it has nothing to do
with competence, but it has
a lot to do with interest.
And because you have to be very interested
in things to go be an engineer because
that's all you're going to be doing if
you're an engineer, then only those people
who are extremely interested in things
tend to become engineers
and most of them are men.
And that's why even in places like
Scandinavia, where a tremendous amount
of effort has been put into flattening
the sociocultural landscape
and successfully, by the way,
there's still a preponderance of male
engineers and there's
a preponderance of female nurses.
And no matter how much sociological
gerrymandering goes on,
those statistics have remained quite
intractable over about a 15 year period.
And so there are differences.
There are differences.
They're not massive.
And then you might ask, well,
are those sociocultural or biological?
It's like well, that's a hard question
to answer because it depends on how much
variability there is
in the sociocultural landscape.
Because the proportion by which something
is biological versus sociocultural
varies with the sociocultural landscape.
That's a complicated thing to digest
because you think of those things
as fixed, but they're not.
But what we have demonstrated quite
clearly and this is mainstream science
despite the fact that people don't like
it, that this test has already been done.
So we developed a personality model that's
pretty stable across cultures,
purely derived from statistical
from statistical processes.
An atheoretical model if there ever was
one, and quite an unattractive
model because of that conceptually.
But that's beside the point.
Then we saw across culturally whether
there were differences in the fundamental
temperaments of men and women.
And the answer was yes.
Cross culturally, quite robust.
Women are higher in the experience
of anxiety and emotional pain and they're
more compassionate and agreeable.
Those are the big differences.
And there are differences of a magnitude
that I already pointed out.
Then the next question is, well,
to what degree is that biological
versus sociocultural?
And it's complicated because that variable
depends on the sociocultural landscape.
But we'll put that aside.
You can determine that by stacking up
countries from those who have
done everything they possibly can
to flatten out the sociocultural landscape
in relationship to gender,
to those who haven't that are
still very stratified by by sex.
And then what you do is you look
at the magnitude of the temperament
differences in keeping
with the variability that those countries
have in terms of their socio cultural
egalitarianism and the sociocultural
types, the social constructionists.
Their prediction is as cultures become
more egalitarian,
men and women become more different.
More the same.
Sorry, more the same
because it's environmental.
That isn't what happens exactly.
The opposite happens.
As you flatten out the sociocultural
landscape, men and women
become more different.
The data is in.
The experiment is done.
Tens of thousands of people,
multiple countries, and it's
not what anyone expected.
And you might think think, well,
it's all the right wing psychologists.
It's like all the right wing psychologists
are in this room, sitting in this chair.